## Dr Mélodie Monod

CONTACT

Professional email: melodie.monod@novartis.com

Personal email: monod.melodie@gmail.com

**Phone:** +353 858803225

Website: https://melodiemonod.github.io/

**PROFILE** 

DETAILS

I am a dedicated professional who have led and produced high impact work (published in journals such as Nature and Science) that has garnered 5k+ citations. My expertise lies in utilizing scalable Bayesian methods and models to gain a comprehensive understanding of complex public health and biological phenomena. I have experience in spatio-temporal models, survival models, computer vision models and scalable inference techniques.

**EXPERIENCE** 

### Novartis, Dublin, Ireland

Since January 2023

Principal Biostatistician

I am developing original statistical methods for pharmaceutical applications. I am also concurrently collaborating on a joint initiative with the FDA to integrate MRI data for survival prediction using deep learning.

### Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom

Since April 2023

Academic Visitor

I engage to ongoing research collaborations with academic faculty, PhD students, and MSc students.

Novartis, Basel, Switzerland

06/2021 - 09/2021

Advanced Explanatory Analysis Intern Supervisor: Dr. Sebastian Weber

I have developed a time-to-first-event safety model that uses pharmacokinetic principles in the context of phase I oncology dose-escalation trials with multiple schedules.

## University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland

07/2017 - 09/2017

Summer Research Assistant
Supervisor: Dr. Bernard Cerutti

I have investigated cross-sectional medical data from the Hospital of Geneva to determine optimal training schedule for health personnel.

EDUCATION

### Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom

2019-2023

PhD in Modern Statistics and Statistical Machine Learning

Thesis title: Bayesian models and methods to estimate age-specific infectious disease transmission dynamics: integrating disease surveillance time series, mobility, and vaccination data

Supervisors: Dr. Oliver Ratmann, Prof. Samir Bhatt, Dr. Matthew Hall

First student to complete the program among a cohort of 14 students in Imperial College London and Oxford University

### Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom

2018 - 2019

Master of Science in Statistics Final Grade: Distinction

### University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland

2015-2018

Bachelor of Science in Economics and Management

Final Grade: 5.71/6, Class Rank: First out of > 100 students

Major in Economics and minor in Statistics

## PROGRAMMING SKILLS

Highly proficient in R, Stan and LATEX.

Open source code:

- Model for characterizing COVID-19 spread: https://github.com/ ImperialCollegeLondon/covid19model
- Regularised B-splines Projected Gaussian Process Priors: https://github.com/ ImperialCollegeLondon/BSplinesProjectedGPs
- Analysis of age-specific HIV transmission dynamics: https://github.com/ MLGlobalHealth/phyloSI-RakaiAgeGender

#### AWARDS

EPSRC CDT in Modern Statistics and Statistical Machine Learning Scholarship
2019-2023

Imperial College London, London, United-Kingdom

The Department of Mathematics Scholarship for the MSc Statistics 2018 Imperial College London, London, United-Kingdom

Awarded for academic excellence and ability to continue into a postgraduate research degree.

Highest overall grade average of the Bachelor's Degree in Economics and Management - Major Economics 2018 University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland

### TALKS

StanCon 2020

2020

COVID-19 Dynamics & Evolution Webinar Series, University of California San Diego 2020

Banff International Research Station for Mathematical Innovation and Discovery 2021

### ISBA 2022 World Meeting

2022

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Mélodie Monod, et al. Longitudinal population-level HIV epidemiologic and genomic surveillance highlights growing gender disparity of HIV transmission in Uganda. *Nature Microbiology*, December 2023. doi: 10.1038/s41564-023-01530-8.

Mélodie Monod, et al. Regularised B-splines Projected Gaussian Process Priors to Estimate Time-trends in Age-specific COVID-19 Deaths. *Bayesian Analysis*, January 2022. doi: 10.1214/22-ba1334.

Alexandra Blenkinsop, Mélodie Monod, et al. Estimating the potential to prevent locally acquired HIV infections in a UNAIDS fast-track city, Amsterdam. eLife, 11, August 2022. doi: 10.7554/elife.76487.

Mélodie Monod, et al. Age groups that sustain resurging COVID-19 epidemics in the united states. *Science*, 371(6536), March 2021. doi: 10.1126/science.abe8372.

Seth Flaxman, Swapnil Mishra, Axel Gandy, H. Juliette T. Unwin, Thomas A. Mellan, Helen Coupland, Charles Whittaker, Harrison Zhu, Tresnia Berah, Jeffrey W. Eaton, Mélodie Monod, Imperial COllege COVID-19 Response Team, Azra C. Ghani, Christl A. Donnelly, Steven Riley, Michaela A. C. Vollmer, Neil M. Ferguson, Lucy C. Okell, and Samir Bhatt and. Estimating the effects of non-pharmaceutical interventions on COVID-19 in Europe. *Nature*, 584(7820):257–261, June 2020. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2405-7.

# FURTHER PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Shozen Dan, Yu Chen, Yining Chen, Melodie Monod, Veronika K. Jaeger, Samir Bhatt, André Karch, and Oliver Ratmann and. Estimating fine age structure and time trends in human contact patterns from coarse contact data: The bayesian rate consistency model. *PLOS Computational Biology*, 19(6):e1011191, June 2023. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011191. URL https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011191.
- [2] Alexandra Blenkinsop, Mélodie Monod, Ard van Sighem, Nikos Pantazis, Daniela Bezemer, Eline Op de Coul, Thijs van de Laar, Christophe Fraser, Maria Prins, Peter Reiss, Godelieve J de Bree, and Oliver Ratmann and. Estimating the potential to prevent locally acquired HIV infections in a UNAIDS fast-track city, amsterdam. eLife, 11, August 2022. doi: 10.7554/elife.76487. URL https://doi.org/10.7554/elife.76487.
- [3] Andrea Brizzi, Charles Whittaker, Luciana M. S. Servo, Iwona Hawryluk, Carlos A. Prete, William M. de Souza, Renato S. Aguiar, Leonardo J. T. Araujo, Leonardo S. Bastos, Alexandra Blenkinsop, Lewis F. Buss, Darlan Candido, Marcia C. Castro, Silvia F. Costa, Julio Croda, Andreza Aruska de Souza Santos, Christopher Dye, Seth Flaxman, Paula L. C. Fonseca, Victor E. V. Geddes, Bernardo Gutierrez, Philippe Lemey, Anna S. Levin, Thomas Mellan, Diego M. Bonfim, Xenia Miscouridou, Swapnil Mishra, Mélodie Monod, Filipe R. R. Moreira, Bruce Nelson, Rafael H. M. Pereira, Otavio Ranzani, Ricardo P. Schnekenberg, Elizaveta Semenova, Raphael Sonabend, Renan P. Souza, Xiaoyue Xi, Ester C. Sabino, Nuno R. Faria, Samir Bhatt, and Oliver Ratmann. Spatial and temporal fluctuations in COVID-19 fatality rates in brazilian hospitals. Nature Medicine, 28(7):1476–1485, May 2022. doi: 10.1038/s41591-022-01807-1. URL https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-022-01807-1.
- [4] Andria Mousa, Peter Winskill, Oliver John Watson, Oliver Ratmann, Mélodie Monod, Marco Ajelli, Aldiouma Diallo, Peter J Dodd, Carlos G Grijalva, Moses Chapa Kiti, Anand Krishnan, Rakesh Kumar, Supriya Kumar, Kin O Kwok, Claudio F Lanata, Olivier Le Polain de Waroux, Kathy Leung, Wiriya Mahikul, Alessia Melegaro, Carl D Morrow, Joël Mossong, Eleanor FG Neal, D James Nokes, Wirichada Pan-ngum, Gail E Potter, Fiona M Russell, Siddhartha Saha, Jonathan D Sugimoto, Wan In Wei, Robin R Wood, Joseph Wu, Juanjuan Zhang, Patrick Walker, and Charles Whittaker. Social contact patterns and implications for infectious disease transmission a systematic review and meta-analysis of contact surveys. eLife, 10, November 2021. doi: 10.7554/elife.70294. URL https://doi.org/10.7554/elife.70294.
- [5] Swapnil Mishra, James A. Scott, Daniel J. Laydon, Seth Flaxman, Axel Gandy, Thomas A. Mellan, H. Juliette T. Unwin, Michaela Vollmer, Helen Coupland, Oliver Ratmann, Melodie Monod, Harrison H. Zhu, Anne Cori, Katy A. M. Gaythorpe, Lilith K. Whittles, Charles Whittaker, Christl A. Donnelly, Neil M. Ferguson, and Samir Bhatt. Comparing the responses of the UK, sweden and denmark to COVID-19 using counterfactual modelling. Scientific Reports, 11(1), August 2021. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-95699-9. URL https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-95699-9.
- [6] H. Juliette T. Unwin, Swapnil Mishra, Valerie C. Bradley, Axel Gandy, Thomas A. Mellan, Helen Coupland, Jonathan Ish-Horowicz, Michaela A. C. Vollmer, Charles Whittaker, Sarah L. Filippi, Xiaoyue Xi, Mélodie Monod, Oliver Ratmann, Michael Hutchinson, Fabian Valka, Harrison Zhu, Iwona Hawryluk, Philip Milton, Kylie E. C. Ainslie, Marc Baguelin, Adhiratha Boonyasiri, Nick F. Brazeau, Lorenzo Cattarino, Zulma Cucunuba, Gina Cuomo-Dannenburg, Ilaria Dorigatti, Oliver D. Eales, Jeffrey W. Eaton, Sabine L. van Elsland, Richard G. FitzJohn, Katy A. M. Gaythorpe, William Green, Wes Hinsley, Benjamin Jeffrey, Edward Knock, Daniel J. Laydon, John Lees, Gemma Nedjati-Gilani, Pierre Nouvellet, Lucy Okell, Kris V. Parag, Igor Siveroni, Hayley A. Thompson, Patrick Walker, Caroline E. Walters, Oliver J. Watson, Lilith K. Whittles, Azra C. Ghani, Neil M. Ferguson,

- Steven Riley, Christl A. Donnelly, Samir Bhatt, and Seth Flaxman. State-level tracking of COVID-19 in the united states. *Nature Communications*, 11(1), December 2020. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-19652-6. URL https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-020-19652-6.
- [7] Nuno R. Faria, Thomas A. Mellan, Charles Whittaker, Ingra M. Claro, Darlan da S. Candido, Swapnil Mishra, Myuki A. E. Crispim, Flavia C. S. Sales, Iwona Hawryluk, John T. McCrone, Ruben J. G. Hulswit, Lucas A. M. Franco, Mariana S. Ramundo, Jaqueline G. de Jesus, Pamela S. Andrade, Thais M. Coletti, Giulia M. Ferreira, Camila A. M. Silva, Erika R. Manuli, Rafael H. M. Pereira, Pedro S. Peixoto, Moritz U. G. Kraemer, Nelson Gaburo, Cecilia da C. Camilo, Henrique Hoeltgebaum, William M. Souza, Esmenia C. Rocha, Leandro M. de Souza, Mariana C. de Pinho, Leonardo J. T. Araujo, Frederico S. V. Malta, Aline B. de Lima, Joice do P. Silva, Danielle A. G. Zauli, Alessandro C. de S. Ferreira, Ricardo P. Schnekenberg, Daniel J. Laydon, Patrick G. T. Walker, Hannah M. Schlüter, Ana L. P. dos Santos, Maria S. Vidal, Valentina S. Del Caro, Rosinaldo M. F. Filho, Helem M. dos Santos, Renato S. Aguiar, José L. Proença-Modena, Bruce Nelson, James A. Hay, Mélodie Monod, Xenia Miscouridou, Helen Coupland, Raphael Sonabend, Michaela Vollmer, Axel Gandy, Carlos A. Prete, Vitor H. Nascimento, Marc A. Suchard, Thomas A. Bowden, Sergei L. K. Pond, Chieh-Hsi Wu, Oliver Ratmann, Neil M. Ferguson, Christopher Dye, Nick J. Loman, Philippe Lemey, Andrew Rambaut, Nelson A. Fraiji, Maria do P. S. S. Carvalho, Oliver G. Pybus, Seth Flaxman, Samir Bhatt, and Ester C. Sabino. Genomics and epidemiology of the p.1 SARS-CoV-2 lineage in manaus, brazil. Science, 372(6544):815–821, May 2021. doi: 10.1126/science.abh2644. URL https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abh2644.